Guide to the William Clair Turner Papers, circa 1960s-2013 UA.29.02.0250
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
William Clair Turner papers
circa 1960s-2013
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Turner, William Clair
UA.29.02.0250
18.5 Linear Feet
William Clair Turner, Jr. earned his B.S. in Electrical Engineering from Duke University in 1971, his M.Div. from Duke Divinity School in 1974, and his Ph.D. in religion in 1984. He has held several administrative positions at Duke, including Assistant Provost and Dean of Black Affairs and Acting Director of the Afro-American Studies program. In 1982 he became a full-time faculty member in the Divinity School, directing the Office of Black Church Affairs before being appointed Professor of the Practice of Homiletics. He has pastored several churches, including his current position at Mt. Level Baptist Church and was previously ordained in the United Holy Church of America, Inc. denomination. The collection documents Turner’s academic and personal activities. Materials include personal and administrative correspondence regarding Turner’s roles as pastor and administrator, manuscripts of lectures and sermons, syllabi and notes for courses taught, notes from classes taken while a student, subject files, and records of the United Holy Church of America. The collection also includes VHS, CD, and DVD recordings of some of his sermons.
Collection Overview
The collection documents the academic and personal activities of William C. Turner, Jr., Duke alumni and faculty member at Duke Divinity School. Materials include personal and administrative correspondence regarding Turner’s roles as pastor and administrator, manuscripts of lectures and sermons, syllabi and notes for courses taught, notes from classes taken while a student, subject files, and records of the United Holy Church of America, Inc. denomination in which Turner was deeply involved and on which he wrote his Ph.D. dissertation. The collection also includes VHS, CD, and DVD recordings of some of his sermons. Major topics covered include black student life at Duke; Turner’s involvement in the Department of Afro-American Studies, Office of Black Affairs, and Office of Black Church Studies; Turner’s academic work on the Holy Spirit and black spirituality; pastoral work in African American churches in Durham; and the history of the United Holy Church of America, Inc.
Provenance
The William Clair Turner Papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer in June, 2014.
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist. Some administrative materials in this collection fall under this restriction.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
Records, such as search committee files or others pertaining to employment where individuals are identified, are closed for 70 years. Some personal correspondence materials are restricted for 70 years from the date of origin unless permission is given by the donor.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Biographical note
William Clair Turner, Jr. was born April 26, 1948 in Richmond, VA to Ruth Randolph Turner and William Clair Turner, Sr. In 1971 he earned his B.S. in Electrical Engineering from Duke University – playing on the football team as an undergraduate – followed by a M.Div. from Duke Divinity School in 1974 and his Ph.D. in religion from Duke in 1984. He also held several administrative positions at Duke; in 1974 he became Assistant Provost and Dean of Black Affairs (now the Office of Intercultural Affairs), and from 1975 to 1977 he was Acting Director of the Afro-American Studies program (now African and African American Studies). In 1982 he became a full-time faculty member in the Divinity School. He taught theology and black church studies, directing the Office of Black Church Affairs, before being appointed Professor of the Practice of Homiletics. His academic interests include pneumatology, or the study of the Holy Spirit, and the spirituality and preaching of the black church. Turner currently teaches courses on preaching and doctrine of the Holy Spirit; he also fulfills many speaking engagements as preacher and lecturer.
Turner has been deeply involved in pastoral ministry in Durham. In 1973 he was ordained in the United Holy Church of America, a Christian denomination started near Raleigh, NC in 1886 as the oldest African American Holiness-Pentecostal denomination. Turner pastored Fisher Memorial United Holy Church from 1974-1979 and Faith Gospel Tabernacle United Holy Church beginning in 1979. In the 1970s and 1980s he was deeply involved in the work of the denomination, participating in multiple committees and serving as President of the Young People’s Holiness Association, a department focused on outreach and support for the church’s youth. In 1990 Turner began his current position pastoring Mt. Level Baptist Church in Durham, NC and was ordained in the East Cedar Grove Missionary Baptist Association shortly after. Turner has dedicated time to working with parishioners in need, particularly the incarcerated, as well as connecting Divinity School students with field experience assignments. He has also been involved with other local ministries and social justice groups in the region, such as the Interdenominational Ministerial Alliance of Durham and Vicinity and Churches for Action.
Related Materials
Allen Building Takeover Collection, 1969-2002, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Black History at Duke Reference Collection, 1948 - 2001 and undated, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Department of African and African American Studies records, 1966-1981, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Divinity School Records, circa 1920-2005, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Divinity School Reference Collection, 1926-ongoing, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Office of Black Church Studies records, 1968-2013, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Office of Minority Affairs records, 1969-1993, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
African American Pentecostals; African American clergy -- North Carolina; DVDs; Videocassettes; CD-ROMs; Black-and-white photographs; Theology -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- North Carolina; Pentecostal churches -- United States; College students, Black -- North Carolina; African Americans -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- North Carolina -- Durham; African American students -- North Carolina -- Durham; Duke University. Office of Black Affairs; Duke University. Divinity School -- History; Duke University. Office of Black Studies; Duke University. Office of Black Church Studies; Duke University. Department of African and African American Studies; Duke University -- Faculty; Duke University. Divinity School -- Faculty; Duke University. Divinity School; Duke University -- Administration; Duke University -- Curricula; Turner, William Clair; United Holy Church of America
- Correspondence
  Scope and Contents
  The correspondence series primarily contains letters written to and from Dr. Turner. The general correspondence subseries is in rough chronological order. Folders for individual correspondents are arranged alphabetically. Types of materials include letters to and from church members at the various churches he pastored, administrative material related to his pastoral work, correspondence with Duke community members as a student and as faculty and administrator, invitations to speak at various locations and events, correspondence relating to various affiliations and community activities, and some personal correspondence with family and friends.
  Access Restrictions
  Some administrative materials are restricted for a period of 25 years from the date of origin.
  Some sensitive personal correspondence is restricted for a period of 70 years from the date of origin unless permission is given by the donor.
  - General Correspondence, 1973-1975 (Box 11)
  - General correspondence, 1973-1975 (Box 1)
  - General Correspondence, 1973-1975 (Box 11)
  - General correspondence, 1973-1990 (Box 1)
  - General correspondence, 1975-1978 (Box 1)
  - General correspondence, 1975-1978 (Box 1)
  - General Correspondence, 1975-1982 (Box 11)
  - General correspondence, circa 1975-2012 (Box 1)
  - General correspondence, 1976-1978 (Box 1)
  - General Correspondence, 1976-1981 (Box 11)
  - General correspondence, 1976-1986 (Box 1)
  - General correspondence, circa 1976-1992 (Box 1)
  - Agbaje, S. O., 1990 (Box 1)
  - Barber, William, 1992, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Bethea, Joseph B., Rev., 1987-1992 (Box 1)
  - Clemmons, Ithiel, Bishop, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Cousin, P., Bishop, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Crews, Rowan (Claftin College), 1996 (Box 1)
  - Duncan, Greg, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Euro-American Studies Seminar, 1991-1992 (Box 1)
  - Euro-American Studies Seminar, 1992-1993 (Box 1)
  - Euro-American Studies Seminar, 1992-1993 (Box 1)
  - Euro-American Studies Seminar - Correspondence with Sheldon Sorge and Prof. Ming, 1991 and undated (Box 1)
  - Fisher, Miles Mark, 1992 (Box 1)
  - Gopal, Arun, 1991 (Box 1)
  - Hall, Joseph Gbana, Rev., 1993-1994 (Box 1)
  - Herzog, Fred, 1990-1995 (Box 1)
    Conditions Governing Access
    restricted until 2020
  - Howard University, 1988-1989 (Box 1)
  - Hoyt, Thomas, Bishop, 1994-1995 (Box 11)
  - Hunt, Michael L., 1992 (Box 1)
  - Interdenominational Ministerial Alliance (Durham and Vicinity), 1990 (Box 1)
  - Johnson, Joseph, Bishop, 1990-1993 (Box 1)
  - Lincoln, C. Eric (Celebration), 1990-1993 (Box 1)
  - Livingstone College, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Ministers Association (Durham), 1990 (Box 1)
  - Mitchell, Ella, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Newsome, Geno Clarence, 1985-1996, 2009 (Box 1)
  - Owens, Alfred A., Bishop, 1991-1992 (Box 1)
  - Shockley, Grant (Obituary), 1996 (Box 1)
  - Restricted correspondence, 1975-1978 (Box 14)
    restricted until 2048
- Sermons, Writings, and Lectures
  This series contains published and unpublished manuscripts for articles and books, lectures, and a large number of sermons. Some sermons on the same book of the Bible were filed together by Turner, and these are arranged in order of the Biblical canon. Academic writings are arranged alphabetically by title. The series also includes 1 VHS, 2 audio CDs, and 8 DVDs from 1998-2010 of Turner preaching at Mt. Level Baptist Church or other locations on various occasions.
  - "Exodus", undated (Box 1)
  - "Judges", undated (Box 1)
  - "Judges", undated (Box 1)
  - "Chronicles", 1992 and undated (Box 1)
  - "Isaiah, Jeremiah", undated (Box 1)
  - "Jeremiah", undated (Box 1)
  - "Ezekiel", undated (Box 1)
  - "Luke", undated (Box 1)
  - Sermons on Luke, undated (Box 2)
  - Sermons on Luke, Acts, and other topics, undated (Box 2)
  - "John and other Misc.", undated (Box 2)
  - "Acts", undated (Box 2)
  - "Romans, etc.", undated (Box 2)
  - Sermons on Romans, undated (Box 2)
  - Sermons on Romans, undated (Box 2)
  - Sermons on Romans, undated (Box 2)
  - "Colossians", undated (Box 2)
  - Sermons, undated (Box 2)
  - Sermons, undated (Box 2)
  - Sermons, undated (Box 2)
  - Sermons, undated (Box 2)
  - Sermons, undated (Box 2)
  - Sermons, undated (Box 2)
  - Sermons, undated (Box 2)
  - Sermons, undated (Box 2)
  - Sermons, undated (Box 2)
  - Sermons, undated (Box 2)
  - Sermons, undated (Box 2)
  - Sermons, undated (Box 2)
  - Sermons, undated (Box 2)
  - Sermons, undated (Box 3)
  - Sermons, undated (Box 3)
  - Sermons, undated (Box 3)
  - Sermons, undated (Box 3)
  - Sermons, undated (Box 3)
  - Sermons, undated (Box 3)
  - Sermons, undated (Box 3)
  - Sermons and eulogies, 1993-1994 and undated (Box 3)
  - Sermons and eulogies, 1993-1994 and undated (Box 3)
  - Sermons and eulogies, 1993-1994 and undated (Box 3)
  - Published sermons and devotional literature, 1973-1993 and undated (Box 3)
  - "Seeing the Lord and Five Other Sermons", undated (Box 3)
  - "The Fruit of the Spirit" draft, undated (Box 3)
  - Sermons and church notes, undated (Box 3)
  - Sermon drafts and notes, undated (Box 3)
  - Sermon drafts and notes, undated (Box 3)
  - Sermon drafts and notes, undated (Box 3)
  - Sermon drafts and notes, undated (Box 3)
  - Drafts and notes for sermons, notebook 1, undated (Box 3)
  - Drafts and notes for sermons, notebook 2, undated (Box 3)
  - Academic reprints, 1989-2005 and undated (Box 3)
  - "The Crisis in the United Holy Church: A Propaedeutic", circa 1981 (Box 3)
  - "The Evangelical Character of Black Religion: Black Evangelicalism" drafts, undated (Box 3)
  - "Lord, Let the Holy Ghost Come on Down: Pheumatology and Black Liberation Theology" final version, undated (Box 3)
  - "Lord, Let the Holy Ghost Come on Down: Pheumatology and Black Liberation Theology" final version, undated (Box 3)
  - "Lord, Let the Holy Ghost Come on Down" drafts, undated (Box 3)
  - "Lord, Let the Holy Ghost Come on Down" drafts, undated (Box 3)
  - "Lord, Let the Holy Ghost Come on Down" drafts, undated (Box 4)
  - "Lord, Let the Holy Ghost Come on Down" drafts, undated (Box 4)
  - "Lord, Let the Holy Ghost Come on Down" drafts, undated (Box 4)
  - "Writing Projects: On the Holy Spirit", undated (Box 4)
  - "Pneumatic Writing, Vol. 1", undated (Box 4)
  - "Pneumatic Writings, Vol. 2 - Delivered at Churches", undated (Box 4)
  - "Vol. 3" [Pneumatic Writings?], undated (Box 4)
  - "Pneumatology: Euro-American Seminar", 1992 (Box 4)
  - "American Academy of Religion Euro-American Theology Seminar", 1991 and undated (Box 4)
  - Euro-American Seminar, 1992 and undated (Box 4)
  - "To Daddy William and Mother Dear: Three Essays", undated (Box 4)
  - Academic drafts and unpublished papers, undated (Box 4)
  - Academic drafts and unpublished papers, undated (Box 4)
  - Academic drafts and unpublished papers, undated (Box 4)
  - Academic drafts and unpublished papers, undated (Box 4)
  - Emmanuel College: "God in Public Space" and "The Holy Spirit: The Giver of Life, Love and Liberty", undated (Box 4)
  - Lectures and speeches, 1994 and undated (Box 4)
  - Lectures and speeches, 1995 and undated (Box 4)
  - Lectures and speeches, 1995-1996 and undated (Box 4)
  - Lectures and speeches, undated (Box 4)
  - Lectures and speeches, undated (Box 4)
  - VHS, 1998 (Box 14)
  - Audio and Video recordings, 2009-2012 and undated (Box 14)
- Duke University Materials
  This series pertains to Turner’s time as a staff and faculty member at Duke University. He served as acting director of the Department of Afro-American Studies (formerly known as Black Studies and now African and African American Studies), dean of the Office of Black Affairs (now Office of Minority Affairs), and Professor of Homiletics at Duke Divinity School. He was also involved with the Divinity School's Office of Black Church Studies. Course materials include syllabi and planning/lecture notes for courses he taught; they are arranged alphabetically by course code where known. Materials in the other sub-groups contain administrative materials and are arranged chronologically.
  - BCS 100 Introduction to Black Theology, 1984-1986 (Box 6)
  - "BCS 124 Volume I", circa 1984-1989 (Box 6)
  - "BCS 124 Volume II", circa 1984-1989 (Box 6)
  - BCS 124 The Black Church in America, miscellaneous, 1987-1992 (Box 6)
  - "1992 Collection BCS 124" (Box 6)
  - BCS 124 The Black Church in America, course notes, undated (Box 6)
  - BCS 124 The Black Church in America, course notes, undated (Box 6)
  - BCS 126 Black Religion and Social Conflicts in America, 1982-1993 (Box 6)
  - BCS 126 Black Religion and Social Conflicts in America, 1982-1993 (Box 6)
  - "BCS 126, etc.", Fall 1983 (Box 6)
  - BCS 126 Black Religion and Social Conflicts in America, Fall 1993 (Box 6)
  - BCS 126 Black Religion and Social Conflicts in America, Fall 1993 (Box 6)
  - BCS 126 Black Religion and Social Conflicts in America, Fall 1993 (Box 6)
  - BCS 144 Topics in Black Church History, 1989-1995 (Box 6)
  - BCS 168 Leadership in the African-American Churches for the Twenty-First Century, Fall 1993 (Box 6)
    Course taught by a different instructor
  - BCS 192 African-American Spirituality, Fall 1996 (Box 6)
  - Black Studies 113 Introduction to African Philosophy, Fall 1976 (Box 6)
  - Black Studies 113 Introduction to African Philosophy, Fall 1976 (Box 6)
  - Black Studies 113 Introduction to African Philosophy, Fall 1976 (Box 6)
  - CHURCHMIN 120 The Holy Spirit and Ministry, Fall 2007 (Box 6)
  - CHURCHMIN 120 The Holy Spirit and Ministry course notes, undated (Box 6)
  - CM 10 The Church's Ministry, 1987-1989 (Box 6)
  - CM 10 The Church's Ministry course notes, circa 1991 (Box 6)
  - CM 10 The Church's Ministry, Fall 1992 (Box 6)
  - CM 10 The Church's Ministry, Fall 1992 (Box 6)
  - CM 10 The Church's Ministry, Fall 1992 (Box 6)
  - CM 10 The Church's Ministry, Fall 1992 (Oversize-box 15)
  - CM 10 The Church's Ministry, undated (Box 6)
  - "CM 10 Documents", undated (Box 6)
  - CT 32 Introduction to Christian Theology, 1986-1993 (Box 6)
  - CT 32 Introduction to Christian Theology, Spring 1989 (Box 7)
  - CT 108 Major Types of Protestant Theology, Fall 1986 (Box 7)
  - CT 108 Major Types of Protestant Theology course notes, Fall 1986 (Box 7)
  - CT 112 Doctrine of the Holy Spirit, 1985-1987 (Box 7)
  - CT 112 Doctrine of the Holy Spirit course notes, undated (Box 7)
  - CT 134 Theology of Pentecostalism, 1985-1986 (Box 7)
  - CT 134 Theology of Pentecostalism course notes, 1986 (Box 7)
  - CT 134 Theology of Pentecostalism, 1986-1995 (Box 7)
  - CT 220 and PR 183, Fall 2002 (Box 7)
  - CT 220 and PR 30, course notes, Spring 2007 (Box 7)
  - PAR 164, Spring 2006 (Box 7)
  - "A Sermon Reader, PR 30", Spring 1995 (Box 7)
  - PR 30 Theology and Practice of Preaching, 1995-2002 (Box 7)
  - PR 30 Theology and Practice of Preaching, 1996-1999 (Box 7)
  - PR 30 Theology and Practice of Preaching, 1998-1999 (Box 7)
  - PR 30 Theology and Practice of Preaching, 1999-2006 (Box 7)
  - PR 30 Theology and Practice of Preaching, Spring 2006 (Box 7)
  - PR 30 Theology and Practice of Preaching lectures, undated (Box 7)
  - PR 170 Contemporary Pneumatology and Preaching, "Preaching in Our Current Crisis", circa 2001 Sept. 11 (Box 7)
  - PR 170 Contemporary Pneumatology and Preaching course notes, undated (Box 7)
  - PR 183 Preaching in the Black Community and PR 189 Preaching in Context, Spring 1985 (Box 7)
  - PR 183 Preaching in the Black Community and PR 189 Preaching in Context, 1985-1998 (Box 7)
  - PR 183 Preaching in the Black Community, Fall 1993 (Box 7)
  - PR 183 Preaching in the Black Community, Fall 1998 (Box 7)
  - PR 183 Preaching in the Black Community, Fall 1993 (Box 7)
  - PR 189 Preaching in Context, 1987-1989 (Box 7)
  - PR 193 Theology in Preaching, 1996-1997 (Box 7)
  - PR 193 Theology in Preaching, Fall 2001 (Box 7)
  - PR 193 Theology in Preaching and BCS 144 Topics in Black Church History course notes, Fall 1990 (Box 7)
  - PR 195 Preaching about Social Crisis, Spring 1998 (Box 7)
  - Course syllabi and handouts, 1981-1990 (Box 7)
  - Course syllabi and lectures, 1987-1999 and undated (Box 7)
  - Course syllabi, notes and readings, 1992-1996 (Box 7)
  - Course syllabi, lectures and notes, 1996-2014 (Box 7)
  - Course syllabi, 2000-2007 (Box 7)
  - Course notes, Spring 2004 (Box 7)
  - Course syllabi and notes, 2007-2009 (Box 7)
  - United Christian College course, Spring 1985 (Box 7)
  - Course readings, "The Epistle to the Romans," and notes, undated (Box 7)
  - Course readings, "Epistle to the Romans", undated (Box 7)
  - Course notes and lectures, undated (Box 7)
  - Course notes and lectures, undated (Box 7)
  - Course notes and lectures, undated (Box 8)
  - Black Studies reports and memos, 1972-1973 and undated (Box 8)
  - Black Studies materials, 1975-1977 (Box 8)
  - Black Studies materials, 1975-1977 (Box 8)
  - Black Studies materials, 1975-1977 (Box 8)
  - Black Studies materials (restricted), 1975-1977 (Box 14)
    restricted until 2046
  - Black Studies courses, 1977 (Box 8)
  - Black Studies to-do lists and notes, undated (Box 8)
  - "Black Church Studies Evolution", 1970-1980 (Box 8)
  - "Four Year Dual Degree Student Minister Placement Proposal for the Tent-Making Churches in the Southern Conference," proposal and correspondence, 1972 (Box 8)
  - Black Church Affairs correspondence, 1989, 1995 (Box 8)
  - Black Directory, 1974-1975 (Box 8)
  - Office of Black Affairs, 1976-1989 and undated (Box 8)
  - President's Council on Black Affairs, 1986-1991 (Box 8)
  - President's Council on Black Affairs, 1990-1991 (Box 8)
  - "Report to the President's Council on Black Affairs on the Office of Minority Affairs", 1995 (Box 8)
  - President's Council on Black Affairs, 1985-1987 (Box 8)
- United Holy Church of America Records
  This series contains correspondence, minutes, reports, programs, and publications of the United Holy Church of America, Inc. denomination, in which Turner was an elder and pastor for a number of years and on which he wrote his Ph.D. dissertation. Much of the correspondence is between bishops of the denomination and pertains to a rift between member districts in the mid-1970s. Folders are arranged alphabetically by title.
  - Barbados District Convention program, 1982 (Box 8)
  - Bermuda District Convention program, 1980 (Box 8)
  - Bible Church School and Young People's Holy Association General Convention programs, 1962, 1974, 1980 (Box 8)
  - Bishop's Council session minutes, 1967 (Box 9)
  - "A Brief History of the United Holy Church of America, Incorporated," by Reverend H. O. Latta, undated (Box 9)
  - Central District Convention programs, 1977, 1986 and undated (Box 9)
  - Committee of Concerned Churchpersons minutes, 1975 (Box 9)
  - "Contribution" by Ted Shine; "Destination" by Lorraine Anderson, Marsha Eaglin, and Joy Lewis; "He Leadeth Me beside the Still Waters" by Mary Alice Moseley, 1970, circa 1986, and undated (Box 12)
  - "The Function and Design of YPHA Literature", undated (Box 9)
  - General Bible Church School and Young People's Holy Association Department minutes, circa 1971-1973 (Box 9)
  - General Bible Church School and Young People's Holy Association Department minutes, 1974 and 1976 (Box 9)
  - "General District Records of U. H. C. A. Inc.", 1956-1957 (Box 9)
  - General Workers Conference including Pastorial and Ministerial Retreat programs, 1983-1988 (Box 9)
  - The Holiness Union, October 1974-March 1976 (Box 9)
  - The Holiness Union, June 1976-July 1981, Jan.-Feb. 2006 (Box 9)
  - Home and Foreign Missionary Department Convention minutes, 1976 (Box 9)
  - Latta, H. O. correspondence, 1973-1977 (Box 12)
  - New England District Convocation program, 1985 (Box 9)
  - Northern District Young People's Holy Association progress report, 1983 (Box 9)